Guide to the EDSource Records M1903
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
EDSource Records
circa 1973-2012
M1903
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
122.5 Linear feet 132 containers
EdSource is an organization responsible for gathering and sharing information concerning educational policies and reforms, both in California and nationally. The EdSource Collection houses documents relating to the research, data, and activities necessary to create these resources from 1973 to 2012.
EdSource (Organization).
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection given by EdSource to Stanford University, Special Collections in 2012.
Scope and Contents
EdSource is an organization responsible for gathering information relating to educational policies and reforms, and disseminating this information in various forms to the public. The EdSource collection houses documents relating to the research, data, and activities necessary to provide this information from 1973 to 2012. EdSource focuses on evaluating policies and practices, seeking reforms and improvements in all areas of education.
The collection is primarily comprised of research material and the information assembled by EdSource for publication. This includes reports, case studies, statistics, data, budgets, legislation, surveys, drafts, meeting reports, correspondence, articles, and notes. The information is distributed in several forms, including EdFacts: concise, periodic sheets, usually covering a single topic; EdSource Reports: longer reports, covering one or many topics; and even more extensive EdSource Studies, which in some instances, may produce multiple reports. Reports such as "A Study of Middle School Grades Educational Practices and Student Achievement in CA, A Large Scale Survey of Schools with Grades 6-8", "Similar Students, Different Results: What Makes a Difference in the Middle Grades? A Large-Scale Survey of CA Schools Serving Middle Grade Students" and "Improving Achievement for Low-Income Students: What Makes a Difference" were products of larger studies on the middle grades and student achievement.
EdSource also produced Information Service Packets and Resource Cards, periodic information covering various topics, including ballot measures, school facilities, class size, testing, graduation and dropout rates, collective bargaining, teacher recruitment and retention, education and workforce, budgets, and school revenue. The collection includes the published versions of these reports from 1980 to 2011, and the research and raw data referenced in their creation. Another area of emphasis is school financing; how federal and state money is allocated, and evaluating budget, policy, and funding changes. This includes state and local budgets, revenue, managing resources, categorical funding, accounting, property tax, equity, adequacy, facilities, teacher compensation, benefits, and district rankings. Additionally, EdSource uses school financial data to compare California nationally and internationally.
The collection holds a small amount of audio/visual material. There are computer file versions of the research and publications from EdSource, using several storage mediums, including floppy disks, zip floppy disks, and compact discs, as well as audiocassette recordings. The collection also contains videocassettes and DVDs capturing research, instructional and event recordings, as well as news reports and documentaries on about school funding, academic standards, conferences, anniversaries, state senate programs, demographics, and school violence. For more detailed information on the EdSource records, refer to the collection’s box listing below.
Organization Background
EdSource’s origins begin with the formation of the California Coalition for Fair School Finance in 1976 by the League of Women Voters, the California State Division of American Association of University Women, and the California Congress of Parents & Teachers. The Coalition formed in anticipation of the California Supreme Court ruling in the Serrano v. Priest litigation in December of 1976. The court declared the current system which financed California’s public schools to be unconstitutional. By 1980, these legal demands for equality brought about alterations in the existing laws governing school funding. The purpose of the Coalition was to disseminate accurate and unbiased information explaining the Serrano decision and its implications on California school finance to the public.
EdSource was established in 1977, continuing the philosophy and practices formed by its founding organizations. EdSource believes that an informed, involved public will provide Californians with a stronger school system, civic life, and economy. The organization disseminates timely, useful and accurate information to key stakeholders and the general public. This includes school districts, county offices of education, state legislature, media, organizations, parents, teachers, and other individuals.
These reports are intended to highlight education policies and initiatives both in California and nationally, covering a broad range of topics, including education reforms, early childhood development, college and career preparation, curriculum and standards, testing and assessment, teachers and administration assessment, counseling and other school services, parent and public involvement, demographics, diversity, common core instruction, bilingual education, private and charter schools, special education, student achievement, litigation and legislation. EdSource offers data, research and analysis of any information relevant to education, keeping interested parties aware of important policies and issues.
Collection Series:
Early Education thru Adult Education
Bilingual Education & Diversity
School Services
Community Involvement
Assessment
Achievement
Standards & Reforms
Administration & Accountability
Policy & Governance
School Finance
Publication Files
Organization Files
Media
EdSource (Organization).; Education--California; Education--Research--United States.
- Early Education Through Adult Education
  - Early Childhood Education; universal preschool, parent involvement, funding; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislation, articles, correspondence, notes, 1985-2006; 28.0 folder(s) (Carton 1, Folders 1-28)
  - Middle Grades - General; early predictors, adolescent literacy, struggling students, dropouts, grade configuration, subject development, teacher education/evaluation, high school/college preparation; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, articles, resources, correspondence, 1987-2011; 35.0 folder(s) (Carton 2, Folders 1-35)
  - Middle Grades - General; early predictors, adolescent literacy, struggling students, dropouts, grade configuration, subject development, teacher education/evaluation, high school/college preparation; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, articles, resources, correspondence, 1987-2011; 5.0 folder(s) (Box 3, Folders 1-5)
  - Middle Grades - Study; performance assessment, math & tech advisory groups, organizational structures, project proposals, Hastings Research Project; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, committee meetings, surveys, drafts, articles, correspondence, notes, 1989-2011; 15.0 folder(s) (Carton 4, Folders 1-15)
  - Middle Grades - Study; performance assessment, math & tech advisory groups, organizational structures, project proposals, Hastings Research Project; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, committee meetings, surveys, drafts, articles, correspondence, notes, 1989-2011; 19.0 folder(s) (Carton 5, Folders 1-19)
  - Middle Grades - Study - Hastings Research Project (HRP); includes research/commission/data reports, advisory meetings, school profiles, drafts, surveys, articles, correspondence, notes, 2000-2010; 27.0 folder(s) (Carton 6, Folders 1-27)
  - Middle Grades - Study - EL Advisory & Miscellaneous; includes research/commission reports, drafts, surveys, correspondence, notes, 1999-2011; 24.0 folder(s) (Carton 7, Folders 1-24)
  - Middle Grades - EL Data Analysis Project; includes research/commission/data reports, surveys, committee meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 2006-2007; 2.0 folder(s) (Box 8, Folders 1-2)
  - Middle Grades - EL Data Analysis Project; includes research/commission/data reports, surveys, committee meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 2006-2007; 2.0 folder(s) (Box 9, Folders 1-2)
  - Middle Grades - "National Forum Leadership Training, A Leadership Curriculum for Advancing Middle-Grades Reform", 2003; 8.0 Item(s) (1) trainers guide, (5) compact discs, (2) video-cassettes (Flat-box 10, Items 8)
  - High School & Beyond - General; performance assessment, reforms, dropout/graduation rates, college preparation, K-12 master plan; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, correspondence, notes, 1994-2009; 9.0 folder(s) (Box 11, Folders 1-9)
  - High School & Beyond - General; performance assessment, reforms, dropout/graduation rates, college preparation, K-12 master plan; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, correspondence, notes, 1994-2009; 6.0 folder(s) (Box 12, Folders 1-6)
  - High School & Beyond - High Schools; restructuring/reforms, college preparation, private/tech schools, performance, student risks, exit exams, dropout/graduation rates, curriculum & standards; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, articles, correspondence, notes, 1991-2007; 20.0 folder(s) (Carton 13, Folders 1-20)
  - High School & Beyond - High Schools in the Hot Seat Report; standards, teachers/staff, college preparation, curriculum, drugs/violence, public opinion; includes research/commission reports, statistics, articles, correspondence, notes, 1995-1999; 16.0 folder(s) (Carton 13, Folders 21-36)
  - High School & Beyond - School-to-Work & Career Tech; School-to-Work Opportunities Act, Regional Workforce Preparation and Economic Development Act, apprenticeships, economic equality; includes research/commission/policy reports, articles, 1990-2012; 27.0 folder(s) (Carton 14, Folders 1-27)
  - High School & Beyond - College Readiness; includes research/commission/policy reports, statistics, articles, correspondence, 1993-2011; 14.0 folder(s) (Carton 15, Folders 1-14)
  - High School & Beyond - Access to Higher Education; college enrollment demographics, education code, cost of college, CSU/UC admittance; includes research/commission/policy reports, statistics, articles, correspondence, 1994-2006; 14.0 folder(s) (Carton 15, Folders 15-28)
  - High School & Beyond - Community College; transfer rates, funding, performance, teachers, access, public policy, governance, student fees, dual enrolment, student services, reforms, vocational & tech education, CA population changes; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, legislation, statistics, drafts, committee meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 1998-2007; 35.0 folder(s) (Carton 16, Folders 1-35)
  - High School & Beyond - Community College; transfer rates, funding, performance, teachers, access, public policy, governance, student fees, dual enrolment, student services, reforms, vocational & tech education, CA population changes; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, legislation, statistics, drafts, committee meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 1998-2007; 7.0 folder(s) (Box 17, Folders 1-7)
  - California Community College (CCC) Development Study; Basic Skills Accountability Framework & Title 5 issues, contract info, CA regulation codes; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislature, meetings/conferences, data/statistics, interviews, resources, articles, correspondence, notes, 1983-2011; 30.0 folder(s) (Carton 18, Folders 1-30)
  - California Community College (CCC) Development Study; Basic Skills Accountability Framework & Title 5 issues, contract info, CA regulation codes; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislature, meetings/conferences, data/statistics, interviews, resources, articles, correspondence, notes, 1983-2011; 35.0 folder(s) (Carton 19, Folders 1-35)
  - California Community College (CCC) Development Study; Basic Skills Accountability Framework & Title 5 issues, contract info, CA regulation codes; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislature, meetings/conferences, data/statistics, interviews, resources, articles, correspondence, notes, 1983-2011; 5.0 folder(s) (Box 20, Folders 1-5)
  - California Community College (CCC) Development Study; includes audio-cassettes, 1983-2011; 18.0 audiocassette(s) (Box 21, Audiocassettes 18)
  - Charter Schools; includes research/commission/policy reports, books, case studies, research journals, legislature, funding, events, newsletters, articles, correspondence, 1994-2010; 31.0 folder(s) (Carton 22, Folders 1-31)
  - Charter Schools; includes research/commission/policy reports, books, case studies, research journals, legislature, funding, events, newsletters, articles, correspondence, 1994-2010; 9.0 folder(s) (Box 23, Folders 1-9)
  - Private Schools & Privatization of Education; includes research/commission/policy reports, newsletters, articles, 1993-2004; 8.0 folder(s) (Box 24, Folders 1-8)
- Bilingual Education & Diversity
  - Bilingual Education & Immigration; English Language Learners (ELL) issues, funding; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislature, data/statistics, committee meetings, presentations print-outs, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1988-2009; 31.0 folder(s) (Carton 25, Folders 1-31)
  - Bilingual Education & Immigration; English Language Learners (ELL) issues, funding; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislature, data/statistics, committee meetings, presentations print-outs, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1988-2009; 25.0 folder(s) (Carton 26, Folders 1-25)
  - Bilingual Education & Immigration; English Language Learners (ELL) issues, funding; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislature, data/statistics, committee meetings, presentations print-outs, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1988-2009; 26.0 folder(s) (Carton 27, Folders 1-26)
  - Demographics; includes research/commission/policy reports, news articles, resources, 1987-2005; 12.0 folder(s) (Carton 28, Folders 1-12)
  - Diversity & Desegregation/Integration; includes research/commission/policy reports, newsletters, articles, 1978-2002; 13.0 folder(s) (Carton 28, Folders 13-25)
- School Services
  - Special Education; Individuals with Disabilities Act (IDEA) issues; includes research/commission/policy reports, litigation, legislation, terminology, funding, data, resources, newsletters, articles, 1995-2004; 4.0 folder(s) (Box 29, Folders 1-4)
  - Special Education; Individuals with Disabilities Act (IDEA) issues; includes research/commission/policy reports, litigation, legislation, terminology, funding, data, resources, newsletters, articles, 1995-2004; 12.0 folder(s) (Box 30, Folders 1-12)
  - Technology; instruction & training, internet access & infrastructure, equity gap, funding/costs; includes research/commission reports, newsletters, articles, correspondence, 1994-2010; 10.0 folder(s) (Box 31, Folders 1-10)
  - School Counseling & After School Programs; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, legislation, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1994-2004; 8.0 folder(s) (Box 36, Folders 1-8)
  - School Counseling & After School Programs; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, legislation, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1994-2004; 12.0 folder(s) (Box 37, Folders 1-12)
  - Violence & Safety; violence, drugs, weapons, discipline; includes research/commission/policy reports, articles, resources, correspondence, notes, 1986-1999; 4.0 folder(s) (Box 32, Folders 1-4)
  - Violence & Safety; violence, drugs, weapons, discipline; includes research/commission/policy reports, articles, resources, correspondence, notes, 1986-1999; 10.0 folder(s) (Box 33, Folders 1-10)
- Community Involvement
  - Parent & Community Involvement - Business & Political Party Views; includes research/commission/policy reports, newsletters, articles, 1993-1999; 5.0 folder(s) (Carton 38, Folders 1-5)
  - Parent & Community Involvement - Policy Analysis for California Education (PACE); includes research/commission/policy/data reports, articles, correspondence, 1996; 4.0 folder(s) (Carton 38, Folders 6-9)
  - Parent & Community Involvement; includes research/commission/policy reports, conferences/meetings, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1992-2006; 9.0 folder(s) (Carton 38, Folders 10-18)
  - Parent & Community Involvement; includes research/commission/policy reports, conferences/meetings, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1992-2006; 26.0 folder(s) (Carton 39, Folders 1-26)
  - Parent & Community Involvement; includes research/commission/policy reports, conferences/meetings, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1992-2006; 6.0 folder(s) (Box 40, Folders 1-6)
  - Public Opinion & Public Engagement; status & quality of schools/education, leadership, civic duty; includes research/commission/policy reports, focus groups, surveys, newsletters, articles, correspondence, notes, 1992-2007; 27.0 folder(s) (Carton 41, Folders 1-27)
- Assessment
  - Assessment - Data Driven Analysis/Standardized Testing; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, newsletters, articles, 1998-2006; 13.0 folder(s) (Carton 42, Folders 1-13)
  - Assessment - California School Information Services (CSIS); includes research/commission/data reports, 1998-2005; 5.0 folder(s) (Carton 42, Folders 14-18)
  - Assessment - California High School Exit Exam (CAHSEE); includes research/commission/data reports, articles, 1999-2006; 19.0 folder(s) (Carton 42, Folders 19-37)
  - Assessment - Standardized Testing and Reporting (STAR) Program; includes research/commission/data reports, articles, 1997-2002; 9.0 folder(s) (Box 43, Folders 1-9)
  - Assessment - Theory & Issues; includes research/commission/policy reports, articles, 1993-2001; 12.0 folder(s) (Carton 44, Folders 1-12)
  - Assessment - General; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, newsletters, articles, 1994-2005; 16.0 folder(s) (Carton 44, Folders 13-28)
  - At Risk Students; includes research/commission/policy reports, news articles, 1999-2006; 3.0 folder(s) (Box 34, Folders 1-3)
  - At Risk Students; includes research/commission/policy reports, news articles, 1999-2006; 5.0 folder(s) (Box 35, Folders 1-5)
- Achievement
  - Student Achievement - Study; Hastings Research Project, Hi-Low Study, "Improving Achievement for Low-Income Students: What Makes a Difference", achievement gap, urban education, student promotion/retention, student culture; includes research/commission/policy/financial/data reports, surveys, drafts, statistics, meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 1998-2006; 30.0 folder(s) (Carton 45, Folders 1-30)
  - Student Achievement - Study; Hastings Research Project, Hi-Low Study, "Improving Achievement for Low-Income Students: What Makes a Difference", achievement gap, urban education, student promotion/retention, student culture; includes research/commission/policy/financial/data reports, surveys, drafts, statistics, meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 1976-2006; 23.0 folder(s) (Carton 46, Folders 1-23)
  - Student Achievement - Study - National Comparison & International Comparison; how CA compares, districts, governance, demographics, English Learners, special education, facilities, services, teachers; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, drafts, meetings, articles, correspondence, notes, 1973-2010; 26.0 folder(s) (Carton 47, Folders 1-26)
  - Student Achievement - Study; superintendent interviews; includes research reports, 2005; 2.0 folder(s) (Box 48, Folders 1-2)
  - Achievement Gap; includes research/commission/policy reports, articles, 1999-2011; 4.0 folder(s) (Box 49, Folders 1-4)
  - Achievement Gap; includes research/commission/policy reports, articles, 1999-2011; 6.0 folder(s) (Box 50, Folders 1-6)
- Standards & Reforms
  - Curriculum & Standards; guidelines, subject framework, AP programs, character/service learning & civic education; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, legislation, issue papers, articles, correspondence, notes, 1984-2008; 26.0 folder(s) (Carton 51, Folders 1-26)
  - Curriculum & Standards; guidelines, subject framework, AP programs, character/service learning & civic education; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, legislation, issue papers, articles, correspondence, notes, 1984-2008; 24.0 folder(s) (Carton 52, Folders 1-24)
  - Standards Video - "California's Commitment: Raising Academic Standards for All Students"; includes research/commission reports, committee meetings, distribution, focus groups, drafts, correspondence, articles, notes, 2002-2004; 15.0 folder(s) (Box 53, Folders 1-15)
  - Educational Reforms; state/common core standards, district transformation, assessment systems, school leadership, teacher evaluation, reform models, school financing, site-based decision making; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislation, surveys, case studies, briefs, articles, notes, 1979-2011; 26.0 folder(s) (Carton 54, Folders 1-26)
  - Educational Reforms; state/common core standards, district transformation, assessment systems, school leadership, teacher evaluation, reform models, school financing, site-based decision making; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislation, surveys, case studies, briefs, articles, notes, 1979-2011; 48.0 folder(s) (Carton 55, Folders 1-48)
  - Educational Reforms; state/common core standards, district transformation, assessment systems, school leadership, teacher evaluation, reform models, school financing, site-based decision making; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislation, surveys, case studies, briefs, articles, notes, 1979-2011; 35.0 folder(s) (Carton 56, Folders 1-35)
  - Educational Reforms; state/common core standards, district transformation, assessment systems, school leadership, teacher evaluation, reform models, school financing, site-based decision making; includes research/commission/policy reports, legislation, surveys, case studies, briefs, articles, notes, 1979-2011; 16.0 folder(s) (Carton 57, Folders 1-16)
  - Educational Reforms - Miscellaneous; gender issues, school scheduling, year-round schools, home schooling, gifted students, education & prison; includes research/commission/policy reports, correspondence, articles, 1992-2009; 6.0 folder(s) (Carton 57, Folders 17-22)
  - Comprehensive School Reform Demonstration (CSRD) Program; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, funding, drafts, articles, correspondence, 1998-2002; 5.0 folder(s) (Box 58, Folders 1-5)
  - Comprehensive School Reform Demonstration (CSRD) Program; includes research/commission/policy/data reports, statistics, funding, drafts, articles, correspondence, 1998-2002; 3.0 folder(s) (Box 59, Folders 1-3)
  - Class Size Reduction; class size reduction initiative; includes research/commission reports, committee meetings, policy briefs, legislation, financing, articles, correspondence, resources, 1994-2002; 20.0 folder(s) (Carton 60, Folders 1-20)
  - Class Size Reduction; class size reduction initiative; includes research/commission reports, committee meetings, policy briefs, legislation, financing, articles, correspondence, resources, 1994-2002; 9.0 folder(s) (Box 61, Folders 1-9)
- Adminstration & Accountability